Good morning, בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is ע"ד Ayin
daled and we start a new פרק, perek, כיצד צולין. Keitzad Solin.
So just to remind you, the fifth פרק perek we had done
focused a lot on the שחיטה shechita of the קרבן פסח, Korban
Pesach, שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, some class the when it was שחט
shechted vis-à-vis the תמיד, tamid,
so things that sort of like invalidate, some classic issues relating to
קרבנות korbanot in terms of what you have in mind. And at
the end of it, it got to the actual bring of the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach itself, divided it up into three groups, what
they would do when they were bringing it, the singing of the
הלל, Hallel, the specific prohibitions about owning חמץ chametz when you שחט
shecht a פסח, Pesach, that was פרק perek five. פרק perek six
was the focus on bringing the פסח Pesach on שבת Shabbat and
what types of things would override שבת, Shabbat, would the preparations override
the שבת, Shabbat, the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי
יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, the issue of the חגיגה chagiga which is important
to discuss that there's a חגיגה chagiga brought with the פסח Pesach
and to what degree was that similar and did that override שבת
Shabbat or not. Those are some of the issues of the sixth
פרק. perek. Now we turn, just a second, now we turn, right,
and what happens if you accidentally brought it incorrectly on שבת? Shabbat?
Do we say that you're טועה בדבר מצוה? toeh b'devar mitzvah? Or
do you have to bring a קרבן חטאת korban chatat or not?
Now we turn to the seventh פרק, perek, which gets to the
fact that the פסח's Pesach already been brought, whether it was שבת
Shabbat or a weekday, whatever it was, the פסח's Pesach been brought,
and now we get to the preparation of the פסח, Pesach, of
the meat of the פסח, Pesach, and the מצוה mitzvah to roast
it and the actual eating of the פסח. Pesach. כיצד צולין. Keitzad
Solin. So let's take a look now, top of ע"ד Ayin daled
עמוד א. amud aleph. כיצד צולין את הפסח? Keitzad solin et hapesach?
How would you roast the קרבן פסח? Korban Pesach? מביאין שפוד של
רימון, Mevi'in shfud shel rimon, you would take a pomegranate שפוד, shfud,
you know, made out of pomegranate wood. תוחבו לתוך פיו, Tocho le'toch
piv,
you would insert it into its mouth עד בית נקובתו, ad beit
nikuvato, until it came out from the hole at the opposite end.
ונותן את כרעיו ואת בני מעיו לתוכו. V'noten et kra'av v'et b'nei
me'av l'tocho.
You would put its like its legs and its inner organs inside
of it. דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי, Divrei Rabbi Yose HaGelili, that's רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili said. Now remember, you're not cooking it
with the fat because what you've already done is you've flayed it
and you've cut it down the middle and you've removed the fat
and you've burnt that on the altar. Okay, so we'll discuss a
little bit later about the fact whether there's any fat left over
that might be, you know, prohibited fat, חלב. chelev. But that's not
the issue, but you still have all these inner organs. So basically
he said, so fine, you would reinsert them into the cavity of
the of the, you know, of the stomach and that's
and you would roast them inside of it. That's what רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili says. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, כמין בישול הוא זה, kemin bishul hu zeh,
that's like cooking, you're supposed to roast it, and when it's on
the inside the juices, you know, it's like they're in a pot
and the juices as it's being roasted, you know, go ahead and
cook the organs on the inside. אלא תולין חוצה לו. Ella talin
chutz lo. You put all those organs in a pot and you
put the pot on the שפוד shfud and you hang it outside
the פסח Pesach over the fire, but you don't actually cook them
into a,
actually not in a pot because if they were in a pot
I misspoke, that would be like cooking them themselves, you would actually
put them directly on the שפוד. shfud. If you look at רש"י
Rashi the last wide line at the top there רש"י Rashi says
תולין חוצה לו, talin chutz lo, תוחבן בשפוד למעלה מפיו של טלה.
tochevan bishfud l'ma'ala mi'piv shel taleh. You basically would, you know, put
them on the שפוד shfud as well and they would be directly
roasted over the fire. They would not be in the cavity. Yeah,
if
they're
in the cavity then you have to sew up the animal.
Yeah,
that is true or else it would fall out.
Yeah, that's true, in order that they would not fall out, you
would have to do something like that. I was thinking about the
same thing. Okay. אין צולין את הפסח לא על השפוד ולא על
האסכלא. Ein solin et hapesach lo al hasfud v'lo al ha'askala. However,
you do not roast the פסח Pesach on a שפוד, shfud, now
we just said you did it on a pomegranate שפוד, shfud, but
שפוד shfud presumably without qualifier means on a metal spit and not
on an אסכלא, askala, presumably a metal grate. And the reason we're
going to find out is because if you heat the metal, you
know, it's on a metal grate, the metal gets hot and then
it can and then it absorbs the heat and then part of
the פסח Pesach is being roasted by the hot metal and not
being roasted directly by the fire. And that's a problem because it
has to be roasted directly by fire. אמר רבי צדוק, Amar Rabbi
Tzadok, said רבי צדוק, Rabbi Tzadok, מעשה ברבן גמליאל שאמר לטבי עבדו
צא וצלי לנו את הפסח על האסכלא. ma'aseh b'Rabban Gamliel she'amar leTevi
avdo tze v'tzli lan et hapesach al ha'askala. There's a story that
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said to טבי Tevi his servant, go and
roast us the פסח Pesach on the grate. So that's a problem
because we just said you don't do it on a grate. It's
also a bit of a problem because this רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel,
the one that has his servant טבי, Tevi, is one that lived
after the חורבן הבית. churban habayit. So I will talk about that
in a little bit. That's very interesting and there's something very interesting
to say about that but I will hold that out as a
cliffhanger, we'll get to that later. Let's see where the גמרא Gemara
starts. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, תניתי שמא תחת. teneiti
shema techet. What's the matter with using a metal spit or a
metal grate? איידי דחמי מקצתו חם כולו. Aidi dechami miktzaso cham kulo.
No, because metal, if a little bit gets hot, the whole thing
gets hot. It communicates the heat and therefore even the little bit
that's exposed outside of the animal will heat up and that'll transfer
the heat to the metal inside the animal and then the animal
will be roasted by the hot metal. וקמטוי ליה מחמת השפוד, V'kamitvei
lei mei'achmas hashafpud, it'll be roasted because of the spit. ורחמנא אמר,
V'rachmana amar, and the Torah says, צלי אש, tzli eish, roasted by
fire, ולא צלי מחמת דבר אחר, v'lo tzli mei'achmas davar acher, not
roasted through something else, not roasted through something that was heated up
by a fire. OK, says the גמרא, Gemara, ונייתי של דקל, v'neisei
shel dekel, so still, why use a pomegranate? Use a palm branch.
איידי דאית ליה שיבי, Aidi d'is lei shivi,
no, because a palm branch has grooves, מפיק מייא, mafik maya, the,
you know, the water comes out, the water, you know, that's absorbed
into the wood comes out in those grooves and sits in those
grooves. והוה ליה כמבושל, V'hava lei k'mevushal, and then you'll have water
touching the פסח Pesach as it's being heated and it's as if
it's being cooked, which doesn't mean technically it really is בישול, bishul,
but it's not as ideal because then you have the water that
emerges from the spit that's also part of the cooking process. ונייתי
של תאנה, V'neisei shel te'eina, how about a fig, you know,
something made out of fig wood, a spit made out of fig
wood? Thank you so much, as I woke up this morning I
said I hope Seth brings in coffee.
Oh,
that's good. OK, bring fig wood. איידי דמחלחל מפיק מייא. Aidi d'mechalkhal
mafik maya.
No, because fig wood apparently has some type of a sap in
it, so then the juices will come out or the water or
whatever of the liquids inside of the fig wood will come out
and והוה ליה כמבושל v'hava lei k'mevushal and it'll be like cooking.
It won't be, you know, again there'll be the addition of water.
I, you know, not knowing the agricultural realities one millionth as well
as the גמרא, Gemara, I cannot comment on this but OK. ונייתי,
V'neisei,
I'm sure you could check everything up on Wikipedia there Charlie. ונייתי
של אלון, V'neisei shel alon, why not bring the wood of an
אלון? alon? How do they translate אלון? alon? Do they tell you
what type of a tree that is?
What's an אלון alon tree? I didn't check it up. Fig? No,
after fig. Oak?
Oak? Oak. Oh, OK, oak, wow. All right, why not some oak
wood?
ונייתי של אלון, V'neisei shel alon, של חרוב, shel charuv, or carob
wood, ושל שקמה, v'shel shikma, or sycamore wood? All why there's a
lot of other woods to use. So, no, איידי דאית ביה קטרי,
aidi d'is bei kitrei, because those things have knots in them, you
know as a tree grows like the, you know, the branches have
knots.
So איידי דאית ביה קטרי, aidi d'is bei kitrei, מפיק מייא, mafik
maya, water will come out. Now why does water come out of
knots? So רש"י Rashi says, well if you want to use it
as a spit you have to smooth it. So if it's got
knots you have to cut off the knots. If you're cutting off
the knots, then you're exposing some of the actual skin of the,
you know, the flesh as it were of the branch. Yes?
Okay, can
you
move the car? I'm the only one here.
Okay, so where can I go?
Go down. Okay.
Okay,
so you'd have to cut off the knot
and expose as it were like the flesh of the branch itself,
you know, cut away the outer bark, and then it would the
water would be able to get out would more easily get out
and therefore again would be a problem of having water contact the
פסח Pesach or sap. Sap. Well, I don't know, don't branches have
water don't they water absorbs into them? I mean anything that's exposed
right I mean like if you think about like I don't know
like any fruit or anything I mean it's
got it's not really it's not just it's not water, it's sap.
Whatever it is, any some type of juices will come from them
once you cut away the bark. And therefore it's a problem. So
the גמרא Gemara says, והא
רימונא נמי אית ביה קטרי, v'ha rimona nami is bei kitrei, so
what says the גמרא, Gemara, pomegranate wood branches also have knots? No,
שיעי קטרי, she'ei kitrei, no those knots are smoother and therefore you
don't really have to cut them away and you can leave them,
whereas the other knots are I don't
know gnarlier and therefore they would need to be cut and therefore
the juices would come out. איבעית
אימא, Iba'is eima, בנבגא בר שתא, binavga bar shata, a one-year-old planting,
and therefore דלית ביה קטרי, d'leis bei kitrei, there are no knots.
Of course, if it's a young tree and there are no knots,
then it's not only true about a pomegranate tree, you could have
said the same thing by these other trees as well. OK, but
anyway somehow pomegranate branches are better. ואיכא בי פסקי, V'ika bei piskei,
what about where you cut the branch? Right at the ends where
it's cut,
you know, any stick is cut at both ends, so the water
will come out of there. That's an easy answer.
דמפיק D'mafik into the animal because the ends come out of one
end comes out of the mouth and the other end comes out
of the anus and therefore it's not the juices that come out
of the ends will not get in contact with the קרבן, korban,
right? So that's fine. So now we understand why it's pomegranate wood.
If it were metal it would roast the קרבן korban by the
metal, not directly by the fire. If it's other woods juices would
come out, sap would come out and that would be a type
of a בישול. bishul. Not probably not a real biblical problem but
it would not be ideal. So the גמרא Gemara says מתניתין דלא
כרבי יהודה. matnitin d'la k'Rabbi Yehuda. Our משנה Mishnah is not like
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda דתניא d'tanya it says in a ברייתא: braita:
רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, כשם ששפוד של עץ אינו נשרף,
keshem she-shipud shel etz eino nisraf, the same way when you do
something over a spit of wood the wood doesn't burn because presumably
it's protected and it's inside of the animal and therefore you don't
say oh don't use wood wood burns no it's inside the animal
it won't burn. כך שפוד של מתכת אינו מרתיח. kach shipud shel
matechet eino martiach. So if you use metal the metal's inside of
the animal and it won't get hot and you have nothing to
worry about. So he says you can use metal. אמרו לו amru
lo they said back to him: זה חם מקצתו חם כולו, zeh
cham miktzato cham kulo, זה חם מקצתו אינו חם כולו. zeh cham
miktzato eino cham kulo. No there's a difference between metal and wood.
Metal the little bit that's exposed gets hot and that transfers the
heat to the rest of the metal whereas the wood the little
that's exposed although it gets hot the heat does not transfer and
therefore by the case of the wood wood operates differently wood you
can use metal you can't use. Okay so anyway but you have
an interesting debate it sounds funny that there's a debate about the
physical reality. I don't know if anybody ever tried you know whatever
i mean I know when you have a barbecue and you roast
something over a fire right I'm sure the thing gets actually those
char lines right where the where the barbecue grate is but that's
different because there the grate is directly exposed to the fire. It
is an interesting question if you just have a little bit of
the spit coming out and most of it is on the inside
how hot will the inside of it really get. So anyway so
there is some debate but obviously the משנה Mishnah says you use
wood so that and wood that does not have juices coming out
of it. Okay now we get to a much more technical discussion
which could easily have come from the from the pages of חולין.
Chullin. Let's take a look. First before here we had things that
could have come from the pages of זבחים Zevachim now we're going
to get something that could have come from חולין. Chullin. ונותן את
כרעיו v'noten et kra'av so you put all of these sort of
fats on the inside of it because it says you know that
based on the פסוק pasuk על כרעיו ועל קרבו al kra'av v'al
kirbo right it basically says you roast it all whole together with
its its
intestines. Again the fats if I might have misspoken a minute ago
the fats are burnt on the מזבח mizbe'ach the חלב chelev but
the intestines inside of it on the other hand you know that's
sort of like cooking because they're inside of the cavity and they
get sort of as it were cooked inside of it and therefore
the opinion is that the other opinion is that they get stuck
on the spit outside of it. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. תניא tanya we taught in a ברייתא: braita: רבי ישמעאל קורהו
תוך תוך. Rabbi Yishmael korehu tuch tuch. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says
that when you put this stuff on the inside of in the
inside of the cavity he calls it like תוך tuch inside the
cavity but he also calls it תוך תוך tuch tuch which is
like the sound like a pot makes when it's boiling tuch tuch
tuch whatever yeah. So therefore because like you know because the stuff
sort of boils a little bit on the inside which also points
out to the problematics of it because then it's a little bit
like cooking.
רבי טרפון קורהו גדי מקולס. Rabbi Tarfon korehu gdi mekulas. רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon calls it when you do this whole thing about you
know the whole thing whole and presumably also with the organs on
the inside a גדי מקולס gdi mekulas a goat or a kid
that is מקולס mekulas which whatever the word means it means roasted
whole. So what helmeted?
Oh helmeted a helmet because of right like you have that by
what's his name by גלית Golyat right the what is it the
so okay so does it say why what way helmeted? Because what
is talking about the organs are on the outside by the head?
Well they put a helmet on the head?
Oh that's interesting. Who does he quote who says that? Does he
quote anybody who has that who says that?
No רש"י. Rashi.
רש"י Rashi says מקולס mekulas means with a helmet?
Just as they resemble a helmet on the head of a warrior
yeah רש"י.
Rashi. Where's the רש"י? Rashi? Oh I missed that you're right you're
right you're right I missed that רש"י Rashi you're right thank you.
Okay right before the רש"י Rashis get wide לשון כובע נחושת דגמרינן
מקולסא דנחושת lashon kova nechoshet d'gamrinan mikulsa d'nechoshet it's really right תולין
למעלה בראשו ונראה ככובע נחושת tulin l'mala b'rosho v'nir'eh k'kova nechoshet
thank you I missed that רש"י. Rashi. Okay so very good so
right so מקולס mekulas like the idea means like a so based
on רש"י Rashi it's like a helmet so if you say not
that was on the inside which then it would go תוך תוך
תוך tuch tuch tuch as you were as you would roast it
but it was the other opinion that you would stick the organs
on the outside so the organs are like by the head and
they're a helmet to the head. Okay thank you.
So רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael was going on the first opinion?
Presumably right exactly. Okay
so now it says like
this: תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan we taught. Now you might remember that
we had a discussion of a גדי מקולס gdi mekulas before about
whether you can do roasted meat on ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. And
about doing it in a way that there was a- there was
an- approach out there that would try to make a pseudo פסח
Pesach and would roast it whole. So let's take a look. איזהו
גדי מקולס, Eizehu Gadi Mekulas, but what is this גדי מקולס Gadi
Mekulas that you are not allowed to do on ערב פסח Erev
Pesach because it looks too much like the קרבן? Korban? דאסור לאכול
בלילי פסח, De'assur Le'echol B'leilei Pesach, that's forbidden to eat on the
nights on the night of פסח Pesach nowadays, בזמן הזה. Bizman Hazeh.
כל שצלאו כולו כאחד, Kol shetzla'o kulo ke'echad, if you roast it
all whole. So it's entirely roasted, it's done just like the קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach without a discussion of what you would do with
the inner organs, inside or outside, but to roast the entire goat
whole or lamb whole, that is a גדי מקולס Gadi Mekulas and
that's just like they would do the קרבן Korban and therefore you
can't do it nowadays.
Now,
small exceptions would get you off the hook.
נחתך ממנו אבר, Nechtach mimenu ever, if just one limb was cut
off, or נשלק ממנו אבר, Nishlak mimenu ever, one limb had been
boiled separately, אין זה גדי מקולס Ein zeh Gadi Mekulas and it
is not a גדי מקולס Gadi Mekulas and you're allowed to do
it on פסח Pesach or ערב פסח Erev Pesach to eat on
פסח Pesach today. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. הא דנחתך
ממנו אבר, Ha d'nechtach mimenu ever, if one limb is cut off
even though presumably it's also roasted it's just not roasted whole whole
but it's roasted separately, דאף על גב דקמטווי ליה בהדי טיגי, D'af
al gav d'kamitvei lei bahadei tigi, even though it's roasted behind it-
בהדי bahadei together with it like it could be literally on the
same spit it's just been separated and cut off, nevertheless אמרת לא,
Amrat lo, it's not considered a גדי מקולס Gadi Mekulas and it's
permissible.
נשלק מבעיא? Nishlak mibaya? If it's actually- actually cooked separately is there
any question that it's not a problem? So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר ששת, Amar Sheshet, דשלקיה במחובר. Deshalkia bimchubar. Now what we mean
is somehow you managed to roast the limb without cutting it off.
So you stuck a leg of the animal in a pot of
water while it's connected to the roast of- the rest of- the
rest of the animal or something like that. But as long as
one thing either was physically separate even if it's roasted or was
cooked without being roasted and then even if it's attached, that makes
it not like the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and therefore you would
be able to do it nowadays. So what we have is number
one, this idea that you use a pomegranate spit because metal would
make it burn- would cook the- metal would cook it. Pomegranate spit-
stick does not, a, it's not metal and b, it doesn't have
water and- and sap coming out so it's not like cooking. And
then we said that you would debate whether you would put the
organs on the inside or the outside. The outside you'd have this
phrase מקולס Mekulas according to רש"י Rashi which means like a helmet
it's on the spit above the head. And now the idea that
nowadays you can't do a- whole roasting, it's too much like a
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach but anything slightly different like cutting off a
limb or roast- or cooking a limb would be okay. Alright, so
now the גמרא, Gemara, and I wanted to say before we go
on if you look at the little תוספות Tosafot נחתך Nechtach or
not so little at the top of the עמוד, amud, right, because
nowadays if you could do it if it's not wholly roasted you
might think that if you were to do this by the קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach it would be פסול. passul. What is the הלכה
halacha by קרבן פסח Korban Pesach if you roast it but you
don't roast it whole? So if you look at the
תוספות Tosafot נחתך ממנו אבר אין זה מקולס, Nechtach mimenu ever ein
zeh Mekulas, he says מצוה לאכשו, Mitzvah leachsho, it's a מצוה mitzvah
to do it whole אבל משום הכי לא מיפסל, aval mishum hachi
lo mipsal, but if you didn't do it whole you roasted it
but you roasted it in pieces not as one unit, it doesn't
become invalid. And then he brings a proof from later on in
the גמרא Gemara which we don't have to worry about. So that's
an interesting question right which is what's the לכתחילה lechatchila what's the
בדיעבד? bediavad? So there's a whole question about how do you do
לכתחילה lechatchila with the organs, certainly with the- the meat you roast
it whole, but certainly we know בדיעבד bediavad if it's not roasted
it's פסול. passul. What if it's roasted but it's not roasted whole?
That's less clear. That certainly that allows you to do it nowadays,
what would it- would it be the effect by פסח? Pesach? That
תוספות Tosafot says בדיעבד bediavad it would not be פסול. passul. Okay,
let's get back to the גמרא. Gemara.
Now here jumped ahead a minute ago, now is where we turn
to a חולין Chulin like discussion, a discussion about salting meat and
roasting meat and getting the blood out and so on. So אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, said רבא, Rava, האי מוליאתא שריא. Hai mulyasa sharya.
This מוליאתא mulyasa is permitted. So what's this מוליאתא? mulyasa? Basically it
is you take- you take like- you stuff a bird let's say,
and what you stuff it with is ground meat. You stuff an
animal with meat of another animal you stuff it with ground meat.
Now the problem is what are you going to do after you
stuff it with meat? You're going to roast it. None of the
meat, whether it's the meat of the bird that you are stuffing
or the meat that's being stuffed inside of it, has yet to
be roasted or salted. It's got its blood in it, okay? So
you're using the fire, the roasting, to draw the blood out. The
problem is that which is normally okay, that's a way you get
the blood out is you roast it rather than salting it, but
it's not only drawing the blood out of let's say the chicken,
we're not talking here about קרבן פסח Korban Pesach anymore, not only
is it drawing the blood out of the chicken, it's drawing the
blood out of let's say the ground beef that's inside of the
chicken, okay? Is that an acceptable way because for the blood to
come out of the ground beef inside of the chicken it has
to do what? Get out of the beef and then get- through
the skin of the chicken and out of the chicken. Well, there's
a reasonable concern that on its way out it could get caught
in the skin of the chicken. Okay, so let's take a look.
Now, I do want you to understand before we get started with
this discussion a major principle about getting the blood out, which is
normally we assume you get the blood out by salt, but now
we know that the reason salt works is because it creates what's
that phrase?
Not osmosis. What is it when there's a salt differential and it
and the liquid goes to even up the salt? Anyway, whatever. I
forget. That's my high school biology. Anyway, whatever it is. Charlie, you
don't know what I'm talking about? No? Anyway, whatever it is. Anyway,
the salt causes what? Osmotic. It is. Is it osmotic? Anyway, whatever.
The salt draws it out. But anyway, the Rabbis understood that the
salt also works, well depending on how you read a couple גמרות,
Gemaras, but anyway, that salt works as a type of heat. And
clearly what you could also see is you put something over fire
and the heat draws out the blood. But there's a big difference.
The difference is the following. Is that if I salt a piece
of meat and I let the blood all run off and I
put it on an incline so the blood runs off or whatever,
then I can go ahead and put this piece of meat into
a pot and cook it. If however I
roast a piece of meat, it's not so clear depending on how
well I roast it that I can then put it in a
pot after I've roasted it. Why not?
Because roasting could do two things. Roasting if I do it well
can draw out all of the blood and then of course you
can go ahead and put it in a pot, why not? But
it's also possible that when I roast it I cook it and
I didn't draw out all of the blood. So how can I
eat something if I didn't draw out all of the blood? Because
the הלכה halakha is that blood is only forbidden if it left
if it was if it came out of the meat and went
back in. The blood that's normally inside of the meat, meaning not
like in a like not like you know in the heart, not
collected in a pool, but in the normal like sort of you
know in the blood vessels what's inside a meat is not forbidden
in its natural form unless it's taken out and comes back in.
So for example I could eat raw meat without salting it. Okay,
because the blood inside of it has not come out. So here's
the issue. If I take a piece of meat and I put
it in a pot, I can eat it raw without salting it.
If I put it in a pot, what's going to happen and
I cook it in the pot? Blood's going to come out and
then go back in and it'll be forbidden. If however I put
this piece of meat on a spit without salting it and I
roast it, what's going to happen? Come out and fall to the
ground.
So therefore when I salt meat to put it in a pot
I have to make sure that all the blood comes out because
then it's going to put it in the pot. When I roast
meat, right, I can do something rare, whatever it is, I don't
have to make sure that all the blood comes out if I'm
not going to put it back in a pot because any blood
that came out fell away and now I'll eat it straight. So
roasting actually does two things. Number one is if you roast it
well enough it takes out all the blood and then you could
put it in a pot afterwards, right. And number two is that
even if you don't roast it so well, as long as you're
not going to put it a pot you could eat it because
any blood that fell away and any blood that's in doesn't matter.
Okay, but that's the basic mechanics
of you know getting out blood in terms of מליחה melicha and
צלי tzli for meat. So let's take a look now at this
discussion of this stuffed I don't know hen with stuffed with ground
meat that you're going to roast and hope that all the blood
comes out in the process of roasting. And here you've got a
real problem because based on what I just described, the heat might
be good enough to pull the blood out of the you know
ground beef inside of the chicken, but then it could get stuck
into the chicken the skin of the chicken around it. So let's
take a look. Says
like this. אמר רבא האי מוליייתא שריא. Amar Rava Hai Muisa Sharya.
This מוליייתא Muisa stuffed chicken, let's call it, is permissible. אמר ליה
אביי והא קבלה דמא? Amar lei Abaye ve'ha kabala dama? What do
you mean? The chicken absorbs the blood from the ground beef. So
אמר ליה כבולעו כך פולטו. Amar lei ke-vola kakh polta. The same
way it absorbs it when you know because of the heat and
that caused it to come out of the stuffed
meat and get into the skin of the chicken, it'll spit it
out as it remains on the fire and it draws out the
blood that went into the chicken and goes out and
doesn't go back into the meat then?
Yeah, well that's the assumption that it's all coming being brought down
towards the fire. So the גמרא Gemara says לימא מסייע ליה. neima
mesaye lei. But of course you're right, I mean think about the
the blood from the top part of the chicken, right, that goes
into the meat and from the meat you know has to go
through through two things. So we'll talk in a minute that actually
you might be roasting it not sideways but you might be roasting
it like up and down, you know, so therefore you know like
with the thing sort of faced like the like the שווארמה. shawarma.
שווארמה. Shawarma.
שווארמה, Shawarma,
yeah, exactly.
You know,
so then you don't have to worry about things going through two
things.
You know, if you've got it like this
and here
is your chicken, here is
your fire. Yeah, screw it. Okay, anyway. Alright, let's take a look.
Okay, so that's the argument that that would be okay. נימא
מסייע ליה. Neima Mesaye lei. Let's try to prove this. נותנין כרעות
ובני מעיים לתוכו, Notnin k'ravot b'nei me'av letocha, you're allowed to put
the organs inside of this goat. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Why is
that? What about the blood? Where does the blood go as it
roasts over the fire? So מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, לאו משום דאמרינן
כבולעו כך
פולטו, lav mishum d'amrinan k'bolo kach polto, isn't it because we say
as the blood comes out of the organs, even though it goes
into the skin... I shouldn't say the skin, the flesh of the
פסח, pesach, it then comes out afterwards.
So אמרי לא, amri lo, you could say there it's different. שאני
התם, Shani hatam, כיון דאיכא בי שחיטה דמחלחל, kivan d'ika bei shechita
d'mechalchel, there
it's got the place where it's been shechted and that draws it
out. So what does that mean? It means דמחלחל, d'mechalchel, so מדיב
דייב madiv deih it flows.
So basically רש"י Rashi says like this,
that I don't exactly get. So basically if you've got
here your animal,
that's the neck where its head has been cut off, excuse my
bad drawing skills. Anyway, so here you have all the exposed veins,
right? And here you've got the fire. So because the place where
it's shechted, I guess and here's where you put all the inner
organs. Anyway, since the place where it's shechted is exposed down and
that causes blood to run out of those exposed veins, somehow that
helps the whole flow of blood. So the גמרא's Gemara saying is
if you've put it specifically this way where the בי שחיטה, bei
shechita, the place where it's shechted is cut and you have the
exposed veins, that's causing a whole regular sort of flowing of blood
down, that helps pull out the blood. But in the other case,
presumably דמליתא, d'mueita, we're not speaking specifically in those circumstances. Okay, and
therefore maybe the blood will not come out as well. What? Yeah,
I mean you could have a בי שחיטה bei shechita by דמליתא
d'mueita as well, but for some reason we're assuming we're not limiting
it to that case where the בי שחיטה bei shechita is pointed
down.
You use the other way around?
Yeah, what?
Put the בי שחיטה bei shechita up or sideways or something?
Yes, exactly. So but it's funny why the גמרא Gemara couldn't discuss...
well the גמרא's Gemara going to say in a minute that maybe
it will matter which way it's oriented, but right now we're assuming
that the argument is that it doesn't matter. Okay, so and saying
by the קרבן פסח, korban pesach, if the בי שחיטה bei shechita
is pointed down, so that helps sort of the flow of blood
out. So the גמרא Gemara says נימא מסייע ליה, Neima Mesaye lei,
alright let me now try to prove your point that דמליתא d'mueita
is permissible.
הלב, Halev, if you have a heart, right? You shechted an animal
and you want to eat the heart. So קורעו, kora'o, you have
to cut it open ומוציא את דמו, u'motzi et damo, and get
out the blood that's in the cavity of the heart. And now
you can like... then you have to worry about the blood that's
in the flesh of the heart, but at least you first start
by getting out the blood in the cavity. לא קורעו, Lo kora'o,
if you did not tear it open, קורעו לאחר בישולו ומותר, kora'o
l'achar bishulo u'mutar, and you can go ahead and tear it open
after you've cooked it and it's permissible. Now although it says cooked,
so that would be very hard to understand. What do you mean?
I mean if you cooked it, again the blood went in and
out again. So רש"י Rashi says here בישולו bishulo is לאו דוקא,
lav davka, it means after you've roasted it. So anyway what are
you seeing? You're seeing you have a heart filled with blood and
you roasted it it's okay. Why is that? Why don't we say
when the blood comes out of the cavity it gets stuck into
the flesh of the walls of the heart? So the גמרא... Gemara...
so you see we say מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why is that,
לאו משום דאמרינן כבולעו כך פולטו, lav mishum d'amrinan k'bolo kach polto,
don't you see that the same way the blood comes from the
cavity into the flesh of the walls, it also goes out of
the flesh of the walls outside? No, שאני לב דשיעא, shani lev
d'shia, a heart is different, a heart is smooth, okay so... which
basically means that it doesn't even absorb, the walls of it don't
even absorb. And רש"י Rashi says according to this answer that such
an assertion that the walls of the heart are smooth that even
if it wasn't roasted, even if it was literally cooked, if you
look at רש"י דשיעא, Rashi d'shia, the first narrow line of רש"י,
Rashi, ולא בלע, v'lo bala, they're so smooth that they don't absorb.
Not only does it get in and go out, but it's actually
like you know it doesn't even get absorbed. ואפילו בקדירה נמי שרי,
Va'afilu b'kedeira nami shari, אף על גב דלית ליה כבולעו כך פולטו,
af al gav d'leit lei m'kach polto, we can say that the
word בישולו bishulo means literally cooked it, and we could say that
when you cook a heart with the blood in the cavity, the
blood doesn't go into the walls, which seems pretty fantastic to say
that, like pretty hard to imagine that you could cook it and
you wouldn't be concerned of any blood getting absorbed in the walls.
Charlie?
The blood that is inside the heart cavity is not from the
heart organ itself. Right. Correct. That wasn't known until the 17th century.
Okay, but they did know that there was heart... the blood in
the cavity. Doesn't matter where it comes from.
But that blood did not come from the heart.
I understand. So what? That doesn't matter. The question is how can
you eat the heart after it's been cooked without the blood coming
out of the cavity? Won't the walls absorb the blood that was
in the cavity?
didn't come from the heart. I understand.
It doesn't matter. It's still blood that's אסור. assur. All right, what
about the liver? Yeah, the גמרא Gemara here is then discussing the
liver.
The liver is full of blood. I understand. It needs to be
separate.
Right. It's roasted or technically you really could salt the liver, but
the practice of course is to roast it.
If you cooked a chicken and kept the liver in it.
Yeah, right. Right.
Well, that would be the question. That would be the question. It
would be a similar question as we're dealing with right now. If
you cooked it, that's correct. If you roasted it, if you roasted
a chicken with the liver inside, that would be exactly the question.
But isn't the liver roasted in the oven? No, because then any
blood that comes out goes back in. Right. But that would be
true about any organ that had not been salted. It's just that
they often don't salt the liver and they roast liver they've done
other things. But if you roasted the whole chicken with the liver
inside, that's exactly the question we're asking now. Do we say that
the heat that's drawing out the blood from the liver would draw
it out even if it goes through the skin of the chicken?
It actually happened to me once, I'm sure it's happened to other
people as well. I don't know, they don't do that here because
here you buy your Empire chicken nicely cut up into little pieces
or whatever. But it used to be you go to the butcher
and you buy your whole chicken and they stick inside of it
the liver and all the stuff in a plastic bag. Well, of
course I just took the whole chicken, threw it straight in a
pan. Oh no!
So then it's an interesting question which is does the plastic bag
around the thing prevent the juices from coming out and prevent the
blood from coming out, if the plastic bag didn't burst. Anyway, the
גמרא Gemara here is saying that the heart, somehow like this plastic,
will not absorb, which I can't begin to understand.
I once cooked a chicken when I was very young and newly
married and the liver hadn't been removed. That was when you went
to the butcher and you stayed with the chicken while he was
alive. Yeah, yeah. Before it came all in plastic. Right. There was
no plastic. Right. And the liver was sent and I couldn't use
it.
Right, right. Let's move on.
Yeah. You could. Sorry.
Oh, when I was in Paris I had a שבת Shabbat meal
where the טשאָלנט cholent they had the meat and the other stuff
of the טשאָלנט cholent in the same pot, but the meat was
in a plastic bag. Aha. And they took the meat out and
served that separately and they told me as far as they were
concerned everything else in the טשאָלנט cholent was פרווה. pareve.
Wow! That's weird. Because why did they have the meat in... Oh,
just as a way of cooking the meat. As a way of
cooking the meat. They argued the meat was in the טשאָלנט cholent
not to give flavor to the טשאָלנט cholent but as a way
of cooking the meat. Right. Interesting. Yeah, I mean, if the plastic
bag really prevents any thing from... Of course it's pretty funny. Like,
we say that things go into metal and come back out of
metal. So anyway, whatever.
All right, let's go on to the next סוגיא. sugya. Sometimes you
keep the heart, you're cutting it up and it's on your
plate and no problem with...
No, then you cut it up and the blood that comes out
you can't use and the rest of it...
But it's on the meat and we're not saying if you dip
it in the blood it's not going to absorb?
I don't know, it's pretty hard to understand. All right, let's keep
on going.
When the liver is in the animal, when they say the innards...
Yes. Includes the liver. Right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: ורבינא סבר תפלי האי בר גוזלא לרב. ve-Ravina savar taphlei hai
bar gozla le-Rav. Okay, so anyway we're still trying to figure out
whether you can eat this stuffed chicken.
ורבינא סבר ve-Ravina savar
basically coated with a type of
a batter,
some type of a whatever like a schnitzel type of a thing,
right, a pigeon for רב. Rav. ואמר ליה ve-amar lei and רב
Rav said to
him אי מעלי תפלי הבו לי ואכילנא. ei ma'ali taphlei havu li
ve-achilna. If it has given, if the chicken has given a good
taste into the bread, רש"י Rashi says or like if it's given
a good juice taste into the outer batter then give me and
I'll eat it. So what does that mean? Anyway,
so you see is this supports the position because why aren't we
afraid that presumably he did this and he roasted it without having
salted it before? Why don't we say that the blood went into
the outer batter and got caught in the batter? And we see
רב Rav was interested in the juices that went into the batter
into the outer coating but he wasn't concerned for taste reasons he
wasn't concerned that it had absorbed blood. So the גמרא Gemara says
הני בסמידא. hanei bi-smida. Now that's talking about a type of a
fine flour coating דמפזרי de-mephazrei which is or maybe it's better to
think of it as a type of a like we would have
the cornflake crumbs that
are
very separate. They're not
a... they're tiny little bits and therefore the juices can run out
from between them. Of course it's a little bit strange because even
if it's not a sealed
coating and even if the juices have
holes, have exposed spaces to run out, but stuff still gets into
the coating itself. So it's hard to understand why that should matter.
Let's keep on going. ורבא... ve-Rava... wait a minute... ורבא איקלע לבי
ריש גלותא ve-Rava ikla le-bei Reish Galuta came to the house of
ריש גלותא. Reish Galuta. דתפלו ליה בר אווזא de-taphlu lei bar avza
and they basically gave him... him some coated goose. What did it
say? בר
אווזא bar avza is a duck? Goose, goose! Even better. Okay, right,
אווזא avza is the goose. What's a duck? ברבר. barbar. I don't
know what a duck is in Aramaic. ברבר, barbar, I think. ברבר.
barbar.
Anyway,
okay, so he had some nice coated goose,
and אמר amar he said, אילו דחזיתי דזיג כזוזא
חיוורא, ilo de-hazisei de-zig ke-zuza chivra, if I had not seen this
as it was roasting, the
juices sort of flowed off like glass, it was clear juices
that came off,
כזוזא חיוורא ke-zuza chivra like a white coin, meaning if I had
not seen totally clear liquids as they were flowing out, לא אכלי
מיניה, lo achli minei, I wouldn't eat from it, meaning because I
would be concerned
that there would still be
some blood caught in there. But I saw as it continued to
roast, after a while the only thing that came off was clear
liquids. So clearly all the blood had come off. Of course, I
don't know about that because some of it might have got caught
in the coating and isn't coming out, but anyway he assumed that
once he saw clear liquids it was okay. So you see though
you have to see clear liquids. בי סלקא
דעתך כבולעו כך פולטו, bi salka daitach ke-voolo kach polto, if we
say that it always spits out as it absorbs, מאי איריא כזיג,
mai irya ke-zig, why is it only if it flows clearly? אפילו
לא כזיג נמי, afilu lo ke-zig nami, even if it's not that,
we should just assume that anything absorbed came out. The גמרא Gemara
says, התם דחיוורתא דשערי, hasam de-chivarta de-shari,
that's talking about like white flour which is hard, which basically is
the opposite of what we said before about the סמידא, smida, and
therefore that actually does trap a lot of juices. So there you
need to see direct evidence that all the blood has come out.
So we have one extreme of the light coating, like your cornflake
crumbs, which you
can't prove because maybe there it's got exposed areas and stuff comes
out easily. Then we have the thicker coating, which you need direct
evidence, and we don't know what the general rule is in the
middle. So let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says, והלכתא, ve-hilchasa,
the הלכה halakha is, דסמידא, de-smida, if it is this light coating,
בין אסמיק בין לא אסמיק שריא, bein asmik bein lo asmik sharya,
whether you see the juices coming off, whether they're red or not
red, it's permissible, because
everything would have just come straight out. And even if you have
red still coming out, as I said before, any juices that have
any blood that has not yet been pulled out is okay.
The only problem is when it gets out of one thing and
gets into another. דחיוורתא, de-chivrasa, if it's the white flour which captures
the blood more, אי זיג כזוזא חיוורא, i zig ke-zuza chivra, if
it flows like this white liquid, then שריא, sharya, it's permissible. אי
לא אסירא, i lo assira, if it's not, it's forbidden.
דשאר קמחי, de-shari kimchi, if it's other flours—now again we're no longer
talking about the organs on the inside or the meat stuffing on
the inside, now we're just talking about coating chicken
with a batter or with some type of crumbs and then roasting
it. So as you're roasting it, as you're first getting the blood
out, it has not been salted, is it getting caught in the
batter or not? So we say if it's the thin batter, no
problem. If it's a thick batter, only once you see the juices
are flowing clearly. If it's something in between, אסמיק אסור, asmik assur,
if you see that it's turning red, it's forbidden. לא אסמיק שריא,
lo asmik sharya,
if it's not red, it's permissible, again, presumably if the juices aren't
red once you see the juices coming out, because then you could
assume that there is no longer any blood on the inside. Okay,
now we still haven't decided the מייסתא, muyisa, that's like something coated
with a batter. How about the מייסתא? muyisa? So it says like
this, האי
מייסתא, hai
muyisa,
now the מייסתא, muyisa, מאן דאסר, man de-assar, the one that says
it's forbidden, this thing stuffed with the ground beef, אפילו פומא לתחת,
afilu puma letachas,
even this gets back to the way we tried to say the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach was different, because whether the place
where the neck has been cut is below and helps the flow.
So the one that says it's forbidden would say it's forbidden even
when the mouth of the chicken and presumably where the neck has
been cut is below by the fire. He would say that that
still remains forbidden. ומאן דשרי, uman de-shari, the one that says it's
permissible, אפילו פומא לעיל, afilu puma le-eil, even if the mouth is
above, presumably
that so much believes that the fire just draws it all out
that it wouldn't matter even if the head of the chicken was
pointed up and away from the fire. והלכתא, ve-hilchasa, the הלכה halakha
is, מייסתא שריא אפילו פומא לעיל, muyisa sharya afilu puma le-eil, very
lenient conclusion of the גמרא, Gemara, that you stuff this thing with
ground beef and it's permissible even if the head of it is
above and we assume the fire just draws everything out. Okay, now
one last teaching about or one or two last teachings about this
roasting. Actually, we haven't been talking about salting. אומצא *Umtsa*, which is
basically like a piece
of meat, like a hunk of meat, בי
*Bei* and eggs, which eggs does not mean eggs, it means testicles,
ומזרקי
*Umizraki* and מזרקי *Mizraki* which are basically רש"י *Rashi* says it's what
do you call it, it's like blood vessels like veins. Okay, all
these things are things that have and you see, we're going to
see in a minute, you see that they are very red, so
there's like a lot of blood absorbed in them. So in this
case, פליגי בה רב אחא ורבינא *Pligi ba Rav Acha v'Ravina*. רב
אחא *Rav Acha* and רבינא *Ravina* debated. בכל הש"ס כולה *B'chol haShas
kulo*, now in all other places in the תורה *Torah*, meaning ש"ס
*Shas*, רב אחא לחומרא ורבינא לקולא *Rav Acha l'chumra v'Ravina l'kula*. רב
אחא *Rav Acha* generally is strict and רבינא *Ravina* is lenient. הלכתא
כרבינא לקולא *Hilchata k'Ravina l'kula* and we rule like רבינא *Ravina* to
be lenient. לבר מהני תלתא *L'var mehani tlata*, now these three that
we're just talking about, the אומצא *Umtsa*, בי *Bei*, and מזרקי *Mizraki*,
which are all three scenarios of getting blood out of various pieces
of meat, in these three, דרב אחא לקולא *D'Rav Acha l'kula*, רב
אחא *Rav Acha* is the one who's lenient and ורבינא לחומרא *v'Ravina
l'chumra*, רבינא *Ravina* strict. והלכתא כרב אחא לקולא *V'hilchata k'Rav Acha l'kula*,
but nevertheless but we rule like רב אחא *Rav Acha* leniently. So
they just so we're always ruled the lenient way. Okay, but these
are the three times in ש"ס *Shas* where רב אחא *Rav Acha*
is lenient. Now, what are the three cases? האי אומצא דאטמיק *Hai
umtsa d'atmik*, you've got this piece of meat that's been turned very
red. Okay, now whatever, which just somehow shows that there's a lot
of blood that's trapped in it. חתכיה ומלחיה
*Chatchai umalchai*, if you cut it and salt it, אפילו לקדירה שרי
*Afilu l'kdira shari*, you can even put it in a pot. Now
again, what does it mean אפילו לקדירה *Afilu l'kdira*? That's the point
I told you before, because if you tell me if I roast
it I can eat it, I might be able to eat it
after roasting it, but I can't put it in a pot, because
it could be the roasting did not get all the blood out.
It made it okay, it's now roasted and I can eat it,
but maybe there's still blood trapped inside of it. But if you
tell me if I salt it I can put it in a
pot, that means the salting has got all the blood out. So
putting it in the pot won't be a problem, there's no more
blood that will come out that might go back in. Okay, so
if I salt it, I can even put it in the pot.
שפייה בשיפודא *Shafye b'shipuda*, if I put it on a spit, שרי
*Shari*, it's permissible, I assume the roasting gets the blood out. It
doesn't tell me whether I can put it in a pot afterwards,
but the roasting does a good job. מידיב דייב *Meidiv diyah*, because
the blood will flow out. אחתיה אגומרי *Atchei agumre*, now what happens
if I don't do that, but I put it straight on coals,
not over a nice roaring fire, but straight on coals? That's where
we debate there's the debate. פליגי בה רב אחא ורבינא *Pligi ba
Rav Acha v'Ravina*, that's what they debate. חד אסר וחד שרי *Chad
assur v'chad shari*, one forbids and one permits. מאן דאסר *Man d'assur*,
the one that forbids, מצמת צמית *Mitzmat tzamit*, says what will happen,
the coals will cause it to shrivel, it won't actually
get the blood fully out, and the blood will get trapped inside.
ומאן דשרי *Uman d'shari*, the one that permits it, משאב שאיב *Mishav
shaiv*, says no, even on the coals it will pull out the
blood. והלכתא כמאן דשרי *V'hilchata k'man d'shari*, then we rule that it
will pull out the blood. Now what's not clear I should say
here is, even if the blood, right, even if you didn't salt
it, roasting doesn't need salting. Although I will say there's a big
תוספות *Tosfos* on the coals, it's like roasting. רש"י *Rashi* says that
even when you roast it you need a little salt. תוספות *Tosfos*
disagrees, he says I don't understand the purpose of salt if you're
roasting it, then the heat gets it out and anything that doesn't
come out is fine anyway as I've been telling you. Anyway, but
what's a little bit unclear here is, let's say the coals trap
the blood. Well why is that a problem? I've been telling you,
right, that it's not a problem as long as you're not going
to put it into a pot. Right, who cares if the blood
came out or not? So it might be that we're talking about
whether afterwards you can put this meat in a pot after you've
put it on the coals, that maybe that doesn't do a good
enough job pulling out all of the blood. Okay, or maybe there's
some concern that somehow the blood comes in and goes back in,
that's hard to imagine. So it's not so clear what the big
deal is even if it gets trapped, unless the issue is then
afterwards putting it in a pot. Okay, so that's one issue about
this red meat that's on coals, can we assume that the coals
pull out the blood as is necessary. Okay,
וכן בי *V'chen bei*, and the same is true about the testicles.
חתכינהו ומלכינהו *Chatchina hu umalchina hu*, if you cut them and salt
them, אפילו לקדירה שרי *Afilu l'kdira shari*, you put them even in
a pot. תלינהו בשיפודא *Talinhu b'shipuda*, if you put them on a
spit, שרי *Shari*, it's permissible, מידיב דייב *Meidiv diyah*, it flows. This
is very easy גמרא Gemara *Gemara* because it's just exact same thing
repeated three times. אחתיה אגומרי *Atchei agumre*, you put it on coals,
פליגי בה רב אחא ורבינא *Pligi ba Rav Acha v'Ravina*, that's where
they debate. חד אסר וחד שרי *Chad assur v'chad shari*, one forbids
and one permits. מאן דאסר מצמת צמית *Man d'assur mitzmat tzamit*, the
one that forbids says that it causes it to shrivel, meaning to
get caught into the meat,
trapped in the meat. ומאן דשרי *Uman d'shari*, the one that permits,
משאב שאיב *Mishav shaiv*, says no, the coals draw out the blood.
וכן מזרקי *V'chen mizraki*, and the same is true about like these,
רש"י *Rashi* says this means like I said like veins or arteries.
חתכינהו ומלכינהו *Chatchina hu umalchina hu*, if you went ahead and cut
them and salted them, אפילו לקדירה שרי *Afilu l'kdira shari*, it's permitted.
תלינהו בשיפודא *Talinhu b'shipuda*, put it on a spit, אחתיה *Atchei*,
then we would say ביתא דשחיטה לתתא *Beisa d'shchita l'tata*. So if
here is the one thing
that here apparently it is the section of the neck not just
any arteries the section of the neck where you have all of
the big veins and arteries coming through and you're trying to get
the blood out of that section. So if you had it where
the cut part was below and then that's fine then the fire
draws out the blood. מדידיי, then it draws out the blood. אכסא
אגומרי, Achsei agumrei, so all the common denominator of all these three
things is that there's a high amount of blood in it. It's
red, it's got these arteries, it's a high amount of blood. Why
did it give the example of the what do you call it
of the liver? I don't know. אכסא אגומרי, Achsei agumrei, you put
it on
coals. פליגי בה רבה ורב יוסף. Pligi bah Rabba v'Rav Yosef. חדא
אסר וחדא שרי. Chada asur v'chada shari. מאן דאסר משום צמיתי, Man
d'asur mi-smita, the one that forbids says that it traps the blood.
ומאן דשרי משום
שואב שרי, U'man d'shari mi-shav shari, the one that permits says it
draws out the blood.
והלכתא משואב שרי, V'hilchasa mi-shav shari, and again we're being lenient, it
draws out the blood. Now last case. האי אומצא דאצמית, Hai umtza
d'asmit, you have a piece of meat that became red. חלאי אסור,
Chalyie asur, so its juices or חלאי chalyie is אסור. asur. Now
what does this mean its juices are forbidden? So Rashi says it
means the gravy, but then it becomes very confusing, what if the
juices that come out as the gravy is forbidden, then why can't
I even eat the piece of meat? Anyway Tosafot says, there's a
long Tosafot, I'm just going to give you the upshot of Tosafot's
explanation, which is the simplest. Let me just double check Tosafot before
I tell you. Right. That what we're talking about is that you
took raw meat and you would put it in vinegar or some
type of thing and the purpose of this was that by חלאי
chalyie in חלא chala is in vinegar, right. So, one minute, one
minute. Ah,
so here's the concern. The concern is you want to eat this
meat raw, you put it in vinegar. Does the putting it in
vinegar basically it trap does it trap the blood inside or do
we say that in the process of putting it in the vinegar
some of the blood came out of the vinegar and went back
into the meat? That's the way Tosafot based on the בהג Bahag
understands this case. Just one minute.
Right. So according to Tosafot, he reads it not חלאי chalyie but
היא וחלאי, hi v'chalyie, both the meat and the vinegar are forbidden.
So let's read it again. האי אומצא דאצמית, Hai umtza d'asmit, it
got red. Okay. So if it got red, does it mean because
the blood has been trapped inside or did it get red because
the blood came out and went back in? So היא וחלאי אסור.
hi v'chalyie asur. So if it gets red then if Tosafot has
the גירסא gersa if it and the vinegar are forbidden because the
blood came out and went back in. לא אצמית, Lo asmit, so
if it did not get red, again Tosafot's גירסא gersa is היא
וחלאי שרי, hi v'chalyie shari, it's permissible because then the blood is
trapped without having come out. רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, Ravina says אפילו
לא אצמית נמי חלאי אסור. afilu lo asmit nami chalyie asur. Even
if it didn't get red, it's forbidden and presumably not only it
but the vinegar would also be forbidden.
So he says why? אי אפשר דלית ביה שריקי דדמא, Iy efshar
d'leis bei shiriki d'dama, it's impossible that some parts of or at
least the vinegar is forbidden, maybe it didn't go back in, but
he says at least some of the blood came out. So even
if the red meat did not get red, the vinegar minimally is
forbidden because it's impossible that it doesn't have some strands of blood
in it. And we don't say it came out? Right.
I'm sorry what? And you don't say it came out? Well that's
the question if you have the גירסא היא וחלאי gersa hi v'chalyie
or just חלאי, chalyie, which is a question Tosafot doesn't spell out
the entire גירסא. gersa. One
minute. No, no, no. I'm sorry, Tosafot does say, let me just
read Tosafot.
Right, right. And Tosafot has the first גירסא gersa is when it's
red the meat is אסור asur because then clearly the blood came
out and went back in. When it's not red, everybody agrees the
meat is permissible because obviously the blood didn't come back in, the
meat didn't change color, but the question is whether the vinegar is
permissible or not. And that's where Ravina says that even though the
meat is permissible the vinegar is אסור, asur, there must be some
blood that went out into the vinegar. Okay? So the meat is
unless when the meat becomes red it's forbidden the blood went back
in, if the meat didn't become red is there do we have
to be concerned that there's blood in the vinegar, that's what's debated.
אי אפשר דלית ביה שריקי דדמא, Iy efshar d'leis bei shiriki dama,
Ravina says no, even then the vinegar remains even though the meat's
okay the vinegar is forbidden there's some blood in the vinegar. אמר
ליה מר בר אמימר לרב אשי, Amar lei Mar bar Ameimar l'Rav
Ashi, so Mar bar Ameimar said to Rav Ashi, אבא, abba, my
father, מגלי גמי, maglei gimei,
would swallow the vinegar. He wouldn't have a problem with the vinegar
as long as the meat did not become red. איכא דאמרי, Ika
d'amri, some say Rav Ashi גופיה gufei מגלי גמי, maglei gimei, Rav
Ashi himself would drink the vinegar that was used in pickling this
meat and would not be concerned that the blood had come out.
אמר ליה מר בר אמימר לרב אשי, Amar lei Mar bar Ameimar
l'Rav Ashi, so now Mar bar Ameimar said to Rav Ashi, אבא,
abba, my father, האי חלא דחליפי חדא זימנא, hai chala d'chalifei chada
zimna,
vinegar that he used one time to sort of pickle the meat,
תו לא תני חליפי חליפי, tu lo tanni chalifei chalifei, he wouldn't
use it a second time to pickle the meat. Why? מאי שנא
מחלא מיהא דחלטנו ביה, Mai shna mei chala mitmaha d'chaltinan bei, so
the Gemara says how is that any different than weak vinegar that
we use. So the גמרא Gemara says how is that any different
than weak vinegar that we use to pickle meat? Why would this
be different? Plus, why would you reuse vinegar? Reuse vinegar. What's the
difference between reusing it and using it once if it's, if it's
weak? If you can use a weak vinegar the first time, why
can't we reuse a strong vinegar that, even if it's a second
time? So the גמרא says no, התם איתא לקיפא דפירי, hasam issa
le-keifa de-peiri, there you still have the power of the fruit if
it's never been used before to pickle, בעיניה, be-aneih, and it's in
its original form. הכא ליתא לקיפא דפירי, hacha leisa le-keifa de-peiri, בעיניה,
be-aneih, here you don't have it in its original form. I mean,
here you don't have the original power of the fruit because it's
already been used once to pickle, and therefore it won't be as
effective. Not so clear if this idea of reusing it to pickle
has halachic implications or not. But anyway, it is with this we
end the whole discussion which, as I said, could have come straight
from the pages of חולין Chullin about whether or not, how you
get, how you get the blood out of the meat. Okay, and
we end early actually.